Guide to the McGowan Commercial Company (Plains, Mont.) Records 1903-1968
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
McGowan Commerical Company (Plains, Mont.) Records
1903-1968
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 047
McGowan Commerical Company (Plains, Mont.)
26.5 linear feet 6 boxes, 93 oversize volumes, and 15 photographs
This collection contains correspondence, financial, legal, promotional, personal, and photographic records relating to the McGowan Commercial Company of Plains, Montana, a general store that supplied many of the material goods in this small western Montana town and surrounding areas.
Historical Note
Colonel James A. McGowan was born in Malone, New York,on March 5, 1852. He graduated from Wesleyan Seminary in Eau Claire, Wisconsin in 1868. He then worked for three years in a lumber office and then as a railroad contractor and mercantile manager for 11 years before settling in (Wild Horse) Plains, Montana, in May of 1882. He was one of the founders of the city and brought the first farming equipment into that valley where he was the first farmer. Plains was at the time a boom town as the outfitting center for the Coeur d'Alene mining district.
In 1884 he went into partnership with Neptune Lynch, on whose ranch the city was founded. McGowan quickly assumed control of the mercantile business partnership and expanded his influence to control the entire community. He had great ambitions for the town. By the time of his death in 1911, McGowan controlled the general mercantile (McGowan Commercial Company) a butcher shop, a blacksmith shop, a livery stable, a hotel, the Plains News Letter (now the Plainsman), the electric light and heating plant, the Plains water company and was founder and president of The First National Bank of Plains. He also owned the largest grain farm in the valley, upon which as many as 25 worker were employed. A staunch Republican and great supporter of the Progressive Movement, McGowan served as State Stock Commissioner and as United States Commissioner. He was also an active member of the Masons.
McGowan married Delia Farmer, the daughter of James and Sarah Farmer. He died in Los Angeles, where he had gone to improve his health, on April 1, 1911. His death was widely mourned across western Montana.
The McGowan Commercial Company sold a full variety of items for mining, agriculture, and living. From 1902 to 1932, Clifford H. Rittenour was employed at the store, first as manager, then as President of McGowan Commercial Company. He attended the University of Montana in Missoula.
This collection contains correspondence, financial, legal, promotional, personal, and photographic records relating to the McGowan Commercial Company of Plains, Montana. Financial records comprise the majority of collection items. These materials provide insights into the challenges and successes of operating a rural general merchandising business as well as the early economic history of Plains, Montana.
The collection is arranged in six series:
Series I: Correspondence, 2 folders, 1904-1926
Series II: Financial, 2.5 linear feet and 93 oversize volumes, 1903-1968
Series III: Legal, 1 folder, 1911
Series IV: Clippings, 1 folder, 1932
Series V: Personal, 2 folders, 1895-1901
Series VI: Photographs, 15 photographs, 1898- circa 1960
Series VII: Promotional Calendars, 4 items, 1920-1930
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
Gift of Francis Bates, 1972; gift of Tevis Hoblitt, 1974; calendars were a gift of Special Collections, Montana State University - Bozeman, 2009.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
McGowan, James A., 1852-1911; Rittenour, Clifford H.
Plains (Mont.)
General stores--Montana--Plains
Photographs--Montana--Plains; Business records--Montana--Plains
Montana; Labor History; Photographs
- Correspondence, 1904-1926; Series I; 2 folders
  This series includes two folders of general correspondence regarding McGowan Commercial Company store operations. These materials provide some insights into rural business practices and the early twentieth-century economy of Plains, Montana.
  - 1904-1907 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - 1924-1926 (Box-folder 1/1)
- Financial, 1903-1968; Series II; 2.5 linear feet and 93 oversize volumes
  This series contains financial records from the McGowan Commercial Company including transaction invoices, account journals, expense records, daily transaction journals, check registers, and payroll records. The documents provide insights into the challenges and successes of operating a rural general merchandising business as well as the economic history of Plains, Montana.
  - Invoices, 1936-1967; Subseries 1; 2.0 linear feet
    - A, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - B, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - C, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - D, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - E, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - F, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - G, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - H, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - I-J, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 1/10)
    - K-L, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - M, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 1/12)
    - N-O, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 1/13)
    - P-Q, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 1/14)
    - R, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 1/15)
    - S, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 1/16)
    - T-V, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 1/17)
    - W-Z, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 1/18)
    - A, 1950 (Box-folder 1/19)
    - B, 1950 (Box-folder 1/20)
    - C, 1950 (Box-folder 1/21)
    - D, 1950 (Box-folder 2/1)
    - E-F, 1950 (Box-folder 2/2)
    - G, 1950 (Box-folder 2/3)
    - H-J, 1950 (Box-folder 2/4)
    - K-L, 1950 (Box-folder 2/5)
    - M, 1950 (Box-folder 2/6)
    - N-O, 1950 (Box-folder 2/7)
    - P-Q, 1950 (Box-folder 2/8)
    - R-S, 1950 (Box-folder 2/9)
    - T-V, 1950 (Box-folder 2/10)
    - W-Z, 1950 (Box-folder 2/11)
    - A, 1958 (Box-folder 2/12)
    - B, 1958 (Box-folder 2/13)
    - C, 1958 (Box-folder 2/14)
    - D, 1958 (Box-folder 3/1)
    - E-F, 1958 (Box-folder 3/2)
    - G, 1958 (Box-folder 3/3)
    - H-J, 1958 (Box-folder 3/4)
    - K-L, 1958 (Box-folder 3/5)
    - M, 1958 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - N-O, 1958 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - P-Q, 1958 (Box-folder 3/8)
    - R, 1958 (Box-folder 3/9)
    - S, 1958 (Box-folder 3/10)
    - T-V, 1958 (Box-folder 3/11)
    - W-Z, 1958 (Box-folder 3/12)
    - A, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 3/13)
    - B, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 4/1)
    - C-D, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 4/2)
    - E-H, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 4/3)
    - I, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 4/4)
    - J-M, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 4/5)
    - N-P, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 4/6)
    - R-Z, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Journal, 1908-1966; Subseries 2; 34 oversize volumes
    - October 1908 - September 1909 (Volume 1)
    - September 1909 - June 1910 (Volume 2)
    - July 1910 - March 1911 (Volume 3)
    - November 1911 - July 1912 (Volume 4)
    - July 1912 - March 1913 (Volume 5)
    - March - September 1913 (Volume 6)
    - September 1913 - April 1914 (Volume 7)
    - May - November 1914 (Volume 8)
    - November 1914 - July 1915 (Volume 9)
    - July 1915 - February 1916 (Volume 10)
    - February - September 1916 (Volume 11)
    - September 1916 - April 1917 (Volume 12)
    - April - October 1917 (Volume 13)
    - October 1917 - May 1918 (Volume 14)
    - May - November 1918 (Volume 15)
    - November 1918 - May 1919 (Volume 16)
    - May - October 1919 (Volume 17)
    - October 1919 - May 1920 (Volume 18)
    - May - October 1920 (Volume 19)
    - October 1920 - April 1921 (Volume 20)
    - April - October 1921 (Volume 21)
    - October 1921 - April 1922 (Volume 22)
    - May - October 1922 (Volume 23)
    - October 1922 - April 1923 (Volume 24)
    - April - September 1923 (Volume 25)
    - September 1923 - March 1924 (Volume 26)
    - March 1924 - August 1927 (Volume 27)
    - September 1927 - October 1932 (Volume 28)
    - January 1933 - June 1939 (Volume 29)
    - July 1939 - December 1947 (Volume 30)
    - January 1948 - November 1953 (Volume 31)
    - December 1953 - October 1960 (Volume 32)
    - November 1960 - August 1963 (Volume 33)
    - August 1963 - July 1966 (Volume 34)
  - General, 1903-1967; Subseries 3; 2 folders and 4 oversize volumes
    - Profit and Loss Statement and Balance Sheet, 1903-1911 (Box-folder 4/8)
    - Record of Sales, 1906-1915 (Box-folder 4/9)
    - General Ledger, 1929-1939 (Volume 35)
    - General Ledger, 1940-1951 (Volume 36)
    - General Ledger, 1952-1959 (Volume 37)
    - General Ledger, 1960-1967 (Volume 38)
  - Expense, 1940-1961; Subseries 4; 3 oversize volumes
    - 1940-1941 (Volume 39)
    - 1950-1956 (Volume 40)
    - 1957-1961 (Volume 41)
  - Customer, 1910-1914, 1958-1960; Subseries 5; 10 oversize volumes
    - 1910-1914 (Volume 42)
    - January - April 1958 (Volume 43)
    - May - August 1958 (Volume 44)
    - September - December 1958 (Volume 45)
    - January - April 1959 (Volume 46)
    - May - August 1959 (Volume 47)
    - September - December 1959 (Volume 48)
    - January - April 1960 (Volume 49)
    - May - August 1960 (Volume 50)
    - September - November 1960 (Volume 51)
  - Cash, 1919-1968; Subseries 6; 20 oversize volumes
    - April 1919 - April 1922 (Volume 52)
    - April 1922 - January 1925 (Volume 53)
    - January 1932 - July 1934 (Volume 54)
    - November 1936 - January 1939 (Volume 55)
    - February 1939 - June 1941 (Volume 56)
    - July 1941 - October 1943 (Volume 57)
    - November 1943 - March 1946 (Volume 58)
    - March 1946 - April 1948 (Volume 59)
    - April 1948 - May 1950 (Volume 60)
    - May 1950 - April 1952 (Volume 61)
    - May 1952 - December 1954 (Volume 62)
    - December 1954 - April 1957 (Volume 63)
    - May 1957 - November 1959 (Volume 64)
    - November 1959 - December 1960 (Volume 65)
    - January 1961 - March 1962 (Volume 66)
    - March - May 1962 (Volume 67)
    - May 1963 - July 1964 (Volume 68)
    - July 1964 - September 1965 (Volume 69)
    - September 1965 - December 1966 (Volume 70)
    - December 1966 - February 1968 (Volume 71)
  - Invoice Registers, 1903-1968; Subseries 7; 14 oversize volumes
    - January 1903 - December 1908 (Volume 72)
    - December 1908 - March, 1913 (Volume 73)
    - November 1916 - May 1919 (Volume 74)
    - July 1919 - January 1922 (Volume 75)
    - January 1922 - January 1924 (Volume 76)
    - January 1924 - April 1926 (Volume 77)
    - April 1926 - January 1929 (Volume 78)
    - January 1929 - December 1931 (Volume 79)
    - November 1935 - May 1942 (Volume 80)
    - May 1942 - October 1950 (Volume 81)
    - October 1950 - May 1959 (Volume 82)
    - June 1959 - May 1962 (Volume 83)
    - May 1962 - February 1965 (Volume 84)
    - March 1965 - March 1968 (Volume 85)
  - Check Registers, 1913-1962; Subseries 8; 7 oversize volumes
    - October 1913 - July 1923 (Volume 86)
    - August 1923 - July 1929 (Volume 87)
    - July 1929 - February 1936 (Volume 88)
    - February 1936 - June 1943 (Volume 89)
    - June 1943 - April 1950 (Volume 90)
    - April 1950 - August 1956 (Volume 91)
    - August 1956 - December 1962 (Volume 92)
  - Trial Balance, 1919-1953; Subseries 9; 2 volumes (1 oversize)
    - 1919 - 1930 (Box-volume 4/93)
    - 1942 - 1953 (Volume 94)
  - Bills Receivable and Payable, 1904-1941; Subseries 10; 2 volumes
    - 1904-1920 (Box-volume 6/95)
    - 1933-1941 (Box-volume 6/96)
  - Payroll Summary, 1960-1963; Subseries 11; 1 volume
    - 1960-1963 (Box-volume 5/97)
- Legal, 1911; Series III; 1 folder
  This series contains a contract from 1911.
  - Contract, 1911 (Box-folder 6/3)
- Clippings, 1932; Series IV; 1 folder
  This series contains an article presenting a brief history of McGowan Commercial Company. The article was published in the November 1932 edition of The Plainsman, a local newspaper.
  - Brief history of McGowan Commercial Company, 1932 (Box-folder 6/4)
- Personal, 1895-1901; Series V; 2 folders
  This series contains some records and memorabilia from James A. McGowan and Clifford H. Rittenour. Materials include an unsigned, undated draft copy of James A. McGowan's will. Clifford H. Rittenour was a manager of McGowan Commercial Company and became President after James McGowan's death. These items include records and memorabilia from Rittenour's student days at the University of Montana, Missoula.
  - Records and memorabilia, 1895-1901 and undated (Box-folder 6/5)
- Photographs, 1898 - circa 1960; Series VI; 15 photographs
  This series includes fifteen photographs. Most of the photographs depict Plains, Montana, particularly the McGowan Mercantile Company store and hotel. Also included are five photographs documenting the procession to James A. McGowan's funeral, two photographs of Mr. and Mrs. Clifford H. Rittenour's 60th anniversary, an circa 1950s store anniversary, and images of the 1898 and 1901 football teams at the University of Montana.
  - Main Street, Plains, Montana, circa 1900; 74-47; Tevis Hoblitt
  - McGowan Hotel, Plains, Montana, circa 1900; 74-48; Tevis Hoblitt
  - Main Street, Plains, Montana, circa 1900; 74-49; Tevis Hoblitt
  - McGowan Commercial Company and Hotel, Plains, Montana, circa 1900; 74-50; Tevis Hoblitt
  - Main Street, Plains, Montana, circa 1900; 74-51; Tevis Hoblitt
  - Funeral of James A. McGowan, 1911; 47(VI):1 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - Funeral of James A. McGowan, 1911; 47(VI):2 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - Funeral of James A. McGowan, 1911; 47(VI):3 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - Funeral of James A. McGowan, 1911; 47(VI):4 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - Funeral of James A. McGowan, 1911; 47(VI):5 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Clifford Rittenour 60th Anniversary Celebration, circa 1960; 47(VI):6 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Clifford Rittenour 60th Anniversary Celebration, circa 1960; 47(VI):7 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - Anniversary Sale, McGowan Commercial Company, cake, circa 1950; 47(VI):8 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - University of Montana football team, champions, 1898; 47(VI):9 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - University of Montana football team, 1901; 47(VI):10 (Box-folder 6/6)
- Promotional calendars, 1920-1930; Series VII; 4 items
  This series includes four promotional calendars distributed by McGowan Commercial Company between 1920 and 1930. Each calendar has a large photograph including one of the Clark Fork River near Plains, Montana, a Herman Schnitzmeyer photo of buffalo, hunters with their deer, and Nick Lascu's sheep ranch near Plains.The calendars were transferred from Special Collections at Montana State University-Bozeman in September, 2009.
  - Calendar, 1920; OS 7
  - Calendar, 1928; OS 7
  - Calendar, 1930; OS 7
  - Calendar, undated; OS 7